COTSEN4 COTSEN4
Cotsen Children's Library
- Lorraine Hare, 1983
  - Who Needs Her?
    Children's story about a little girl who is very smart but very messy - her clothes rebel against her in her room; drawings by the author Full mss MKM edits - both line edits and general editorial suggestions Secretaries Nachama Halpern (becomes managing editor) and Judith Sandman Notes on contract from Adria S. Hillman of lawfirm of Green and Hillman; discussion by MKM and Judy Long challenges of working with a young child sent copies of Irina Hale's Donkey's Dreadful Day and some of John Goodall's books; picture of Gabriel attached internal memo about second half of her advance also mentions "First Came the Indians" by M.J. Wheeler-Smith Discussion of other projects: a story called "The Ragtag Circus" + 2 others (unnamed) Usual attempts to sell the book in other countries: to J M Dent in England, to Human & Rousseau in South Africa; mention of attempts to sell to paperback publisher Lots of late letters from Judith Sandman, MKM's secretary, sending copies of books to author Aug. 1988 letter about selling excess inventory at a reduced price
- Elizabeth Harlan, 1983
  first-person novel about a young girl whose father has cancer and who runs competitively; a novel, in the author's words, about "reconciliation and regeneration" (30 Jan 1982) working with agent Richard Curtis; mentions Clare Bell; notes on N.M. Bodecker Line edits from MKM and responses from Harlan Notes on "running facts" from Judy Long - making the mss more realistic; notes from the copyeditor trying to pin down a date for lunch MKM sent Susan Cooper's "The Dark is Rising" to Harlan's teenage sons; thank you letter from son Josh with his thoughts on the books; Harlan sends MKM "The Language of Goldfish" by Zibby Oneal; MKM sends Carolyn Meyer's "The Center"; MKM sends younger son Noah "The Upside Down Cat" by Elizabeth Parsons, his thank you note and response from MKM enclosed application for Bread Loaf conference (or Breadloaf?) letters between Felicia Bond, designer at Atheneum, Annabelle Pike at American Book and MKM discussing Judy Blume and the place of feelings in children's lit descriptions of family farm; trading stories about Nantucket discussion of a short book by Harlan, "Bad, Worse, Better, Best" Good press: Barnard alumnae magazine; hope of being reviewed in Phila Inquirer); interviews in local NJ newspapers; interest in Serialization from "Seventeen"; Harlan sends copies of letters from friends to MKM Interest from Japan and Sweden; eventually a Fawcett-Ballantine paperback edition with a change in the line about masturbation concern over placement of review in School Library Journal (felt it was in the wrong age group) - Harlan's letter printed as a letter to the editor correspondence with Neal Porter, Atheneum's head of Library Services, about book signing and distribution - general concern on Harlan's part about distribution... one librarian concerned that the protagonist masturbates near the end of the book - led her to write an article for the New Jersey Sunday Times re censorship in children's lit and to lead a workshop at Barnard on "the Changing Form of Female Adolescent Fiction" article from the Redmond (Oregon) Spokesman about some parents' desire to remove the book from schools due to its sexual content (June 17, 1987 issue) eventually letting footfalls go out of stock
  Secretaries: Jane Krause (then associate executive editor), Nachama Halpern; Judith Sandman
  Harlan's disappointment with Atheneum's "lack of business initiative and acumen in bringing out and into circulation its properties" - copies she ordered never arrived at her talk at the NJ Library and Educational Media luncheon; taking her second novel to Viking (February 11, 1985)
  - Footfalls
- Helme Heine
  - Mr. Miller the Dog
- Lennart Hellsing and Sven Otto
  - The Wonderful Pumpkin
- Douglas Hill, 1981 - 1988
  - Planet of the Warlord, 1981
  - Warriors of the Wasteland, 1983
- Felix Hoffman, 1975 - 1978
  - The Bearskinner, 1978
    aka "Prince Bearskin" aka "Baerenhaeuter"
    drafts of flap copy handwritten by MKM discussion of bringing out The Complete Grimm includes polaroids of some of the illustrations tale from the Brothers Grimm with illustrations by Hoffman; Hoffman shortened the text of the original story and MKM had a word-for-word translation done also discuss The Rabbit Factory (Die Kanicheninsel by Steiner and Muller), The Bear Who Wanted to be a Bear by Jörg Steiner and Jörg Müller (aka the Bear who Wasn't?) and Hoffman's Tom Thumb Sauerlander people: Margrit Bader, F. Gebhard originally published by Sauerlander AG - American edition printed and bound in Switzerland as well; Oxford considered using the Atheneum translation to print in the UK (Correspondence with Martin West; also discuss "There and Back Again" by Harold Jones and who will replace Paul Binding) - eventually backed out because Hoffman did not actually finish the illustrations - backout letter from Antony Kamm, who had recently been appointed to replace Paul Binding, reply from Hans Christof Sauerländer himself to Antony Kamm of OUP, in German; but it does seem that they ended up publishing it... correspondence with Sauerlander also discusses "The Changing City" by Müller correspondence with Gretel as Felix was already dead at this point letter to Susan Van der Reyben of "Bookviews" with an image credit; interest from Weston Woods Studios (animators of children's books) availability of books on the Encore list
    Secretaries: Nachama Halpern
  - Hans in Luck, 1975
    early correspondence with Felix himself, discussion of The Story of Christmas; later corr. with Gretel; Judy Long; Renate Fischer and Hans (John) Sauerlander MKM and Hoffman discuss the Lore Segal/ Maurice Sendak edition of Grimm's tales
    early discussion about how to keep price down several versions of MKM's translation includes apricot handkerchief printed with "Gretel Hoffman 70 Jahre September 1982" and a silhouette of Hoffman, still in envelope, no note, mailed 12.16.82 correspondence with Ed Schumann Pied Piper filmstrip version (discussions first with Weston Woods) working with Mabel George at OUP, two different translations - MKM's translation included German galleys included; one sheet of English galleys with pencil edits MKM worries to Sauerlander about text running into gutters; letters from Fran Hoehle, Young Adult & Children's Coordinator of the Salt Lake County Library System, complaining about the bindings of this and other McElderry titles; also from Eileen Kemp, Librarian for elementary schools in Hillsboro, OR; letter from Christine Noble Gavan with a newspaper cutout of a short review she wrote (also discusses "The Dark Didn't Catch Me" by Crystal Thrasher) rights to Fukuinkan Shoten in Japan; appeared on "Ladders to Learning," storytime TV show produced in Mobile, AL; good review in Horn Book (letter from head of copyrights and permissions Sally Holmes Holtze introducing herself to MKM) Copy of letter from Carolyn W. Field, Coordinator for Free Library's Office of Work with Children, thanking Hoffman for donation of original artwork for Hans in Luck
    obtaining remaindered extra copies from Outlet Book Co.
- Evelyn Sibley Lampman, 1977
  - Bargain Bride
    aka "Young Widow Mahew" aka "Ginny" - Donation Land Claim Act in OR: married men were entitled to more land than unmarried men; book about a young (15?) widow who never lived with her husband
    working with Marilyn Marlow at Curtis Brown general editorial suggestions as well as line edits from MKM also discuss "The Potlach Family" being selected for Junior Literary Guild 1976 Judy Long (as secretary) sends revisions to Lucy S. Schneider (who is that?) Jacket by Diane De Groat Lots of discussion about what would be an appropriate title Choice as a Junior Literary Guild selection (removal from Bound to Stay Bound, Inc.'s program); children's choice for the International Reading Association, "Classroom Choices for 1978"; nomination for Mark Twain Award in Missouri Christmas card and thank yous for gifts some movie interest; interest from Denmark letters between MKM and Lampman's daughter Linda Lampman McIsaac - mother fell Christmas 1979, discussing delayed progress on Harriet 6 printings
  - Miscellaneous
    Material related to other Lampman books and also her estate "Squaw Man's Son"; "Potlach Family"; "Rattlesnake Cave"; A book tentatively titled "Harriet -- Phil Sheridan's Indian Wife" "White Captives" (1974)
    things going OP; selling extra copies at a discount to her daughters, etc.
- Gunnel Linde, 1984
  - Trust in the Unexpected
    "Lita Pa Det Ovantade" originally published by Albert Bonniers Förlag AB (Stockholm) - contact was Monica Norberg Lone and George Blecher: "This is the story of 9 year old Vesle's great moral struggle to make up for a fit of anger in which she throws her brother's new bicycle off a dock -- and it disappears" (Sept. 18, 1982) Artist: Svend Otto S. translated Patricia Crampton
    working with Anne Rowell and Vanessa Hamilton of J M Dent; also discuss Jan Ormerod's "Be Brave Billy" and Mary Wesley's new book; fantasy book by J. Kennedy; The Changeover by Margaret Mahy, also something they often refer to as "F and G.S." but I can't figure out what that is; Lanky Longlegs (aka "Stein Stankelben") by Karin Lorentzen translation - discussion with George and Lone Blecher readings by Lise Lunge-Larsen of College of St. Catherina, St. Paul, MN MKM's people: Jane K. Doeblin, Assoc. Executive Editor; Nachama Halpern as Assoc. Managing Editor; Judith Sandman as secretary; Judy Long Cynthia Reed of Little Brown re use of "Trust in the Unexpected" from collection of Emily Dickinson poems (letter of 18 Nov. 1983); lots of back and forth between Dent and MKM re most appropriate title xeroxes of jacket and title page mock-ups Lots of back and forth about ending - Judy Long and MKM, as well as Linde and Vanessa Hamilton of Dent; ultimately use ending by Patricia Crampton type face and binding, lamination of jacket; dropping illustrations to make page count work favorable Horn Book review
- Myra Cohn Livingston
  - 4-Way Stop and Other Poems
  - How Pleasant to Know Mr. Lear
  - The Malibu and Other Poems
  - One Little Room, an Everywhere
- Karin Lorentzen, 1983
  - Lanky Longlegs
    novel about dogs, friendship and the death of her younger brother translated from Norwegian by Joan Tate copy of jacket Judy Long, Executive Editor; Jin Lau in production translated from Norwegian, originally published by Gyldendal Norsk Working with Anne Rowell, Clarissa Cridland and Vanessa Hamilton at Dent read by Christine Behrmann at NYPL also working with agents Bolt & Watson (london): also discuss Gail Robertson's Raven the Trickster illustrations by Jan Ormerod; also discuss "Be Brave Billy" also working on "The Haunting" and "The Changeover" by Margaret Mahy, "The Chewing Gum Rescue" Lorentzen's visit to States in March 1982 letter to Tordis Ørjasaeter of Statens Speciallererskole re Lorentzen and Jan Truss's Jasmin changing main character's last name to make her nickname being identical to her mother's make more sense changes between UK and US terminology set of photocopied illustrations full (photocopied) set of galleys with MKM edits delay of publication to Spring '83 and the requisite shipping delays, changes, etc. MKM disappointed with Ormerod's interior illustrations; wonders whether they should rethink illustrations if they go ahead with "Stine Stankelben"; apparently Atheneum Library Services Department was disappointed too! MKM writes to Lorentzen about her more general disappointment with the quality of the book and desire to for Atheneum to design the next one; Hamilton writes to MKM sort of telling her off for writing negatively to Lorentzen; letter for MKM from David Rye, Dent's production director "My Weekly Reader" Paperback Book Club edition of January 1984 - getting duplicate film from Dent payment of royalties - back and forth, upheaval in management at Atheneum also discuss "Most Beautiful Egg in the World" which eventually became "Most Wonderful Egg in the World" by Helme Heine; Gunnel Linde projects
    apparently Lorentzen attempted a sequel, which was not accepted by Atheneum
- Joseph Low, 1975 - 1983
  - Boo to a Goose, 1975
  - Don't Drag Your Feet, 1983
  - What If?
- Daniel P.P. Marolen
  - South African folk tales (unpublished)
- Stefan Mahlqvist
  - I'll Take Care of the Crocodiles
- Carolyn Meyer, 1974 - 1984
  - Amish People: Plain Living in a Complex World, 1976
    Correspondence between McElderry, Meyer, Meyer's agent Joan Daves, and Judy Long concerning this non-fiction work about the Amish in Pennsylvania, originally titled Horses-and-Buggies and Shoefly Pie. Topics include general edits from both Meyer and McElderry, line edits, finding appropriate photographs and compensating the photographers, how to market the book in Pennsylvania, recognition for the book (Junior Literary Guild selection for Spring 1976; New York Times outstanding book of the year; notable children's trade book in Social Studies for 1976), and international interest in the title. Amish People included photographs by Meyer, Michael Ramsey of the Lewiston (PA) Sentinel, and Gerald Dodds; file includes mockups for photo pages. Other topics include Meyer's request for a letter of recommendation for a fellowship at D.H. Lawrence Ranch in New Mexico, and McElderry inquiring after Doris Dana (translator of Crickets and Frogs and The Elephant and His Secret) with Joan Daves.
  - C.C. Poindexter, 1982
  - The Center, 1979
    Correspondence primarily between Meyer, McElderry, Judy Long, and Joan Daves, Meyer's agent, all regarding this non-fiction work about Vitam, a Connecticut rehabilition center for young adults where Meyer's own son was treated. Correspondence topics include Meyer's research for the book, her son's progression in the program, and edits to the manuscript; the original project proposal is also included. Additionally, there are letters between Meyer, McElderry and various employees of Vitam, as the center was involved in editing the manuscript and publicizing the book. The file also includes a series of letters to various radio hosts who might be interested in in having Meyer as a guest; McElderry thought the story would translate well to other forms of media, including television. The correspondence includes references to Meyer's book Rock Band, which she was beginning around the time The Center was published.
  - Eskimos: Growing Up in a Changing Culture, 1977
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry, Meyer, Judy Long, and Meyer's agent, Joan Daves, regarding the publication of this non-fiction work. Also includes correspondence with John McDonald, whose photographs were used for the book. Folder includes photographs both by McDonald and by Meyer. Correspondence topics include changes to the manuscript, use of McDonald's photographs, how Meyer's research partner ought to be acknowledged on the title page, reviews of the work, and ultimately its status as out of print.
  - People Who Make Things, 1975; Chronological
  - Rock Band: Big Men in a Great Big Town, 1980
    Correspondence primarily between Meyer, McElderry, Judy Long, and Joan Daves, Meyer's agent, regarding this biography of the band The Daily Papers. Topics include Meyer's ideas for the book, a decision to scrap the original manuscript and begin again, manuscript edits, design notes, and optioning the book to international publishers. Correspondence includes references to Meyer's books Eulalia's Island and The Center.
  - The Vietnamese: America's Newest Immigrants (proposal), 1977
    Correspondence between Meyer, McElderry and Joan Davies, Meyer's agent, regarding a proposed book about Vietnamese immigration to the U.S., as well as the proposal itself. Meyer never wrote the book.
- Don Moser
  - A Heart to the Hawks, 1975
    Correspondence primarily between Moser, McElderry, and Perry Knowlton, Moser's agent at Curtis Brown, regarding this young adult novel. Topics include edits to the manuscript and Moser's travels in Latin America as an editor for Smithsonian Magazine. Also included in the file are many positive reviews of the book, as well as letters of interest from several English publishers, a Canadian film company, and Danish and South African firms interested in translation. Correspondence with Margaret Clark of Bodley Head, Ltd. includes discussion of Lucy Boston's Guardians of the House.
  - The Last Lordgod, 1979
    Correspondence between Don Moser, McElderry, and Perry Knowlton, editor at Curtis Brown. Moser had initially submitted The Last Lordgod to Knowlton as an adult novel, but Knowlton passed it on to McElderry as he felt it would be more suitable for a young adult audience. Correspondence between Moser and McElderry relates to changes McElderry felt would be necessary to market the book to younger readers. The work was never published.
- Gardner Patterson
  - Docker, 1980
    Correspondence primarily between Patterson and Paula Schwartz, associate editor at Atheneum, regarding this novel about the adventures of a high school boy in Connecticut. Topics include edits to the manuscript, the book's design, other work by the author, and interest in paperback publication by several firms. Also includes correspondence with Richard Williams regarding his cover art and a letter from Margaret McElderry in response to a schoolboy's letter of correction.
- Joan Phipson
  - The Cats, 1976
    Correspondence primarily between Phipson, McElderry, Judy Long, and Marni Hodgkin of Macmillan London, which co-published The Cats with Atheneum. Much of the correspondence revolves around the book jacket, done by Ron Brooks. Brooks was late in producing the jacket and when it arrived it was finished work, rather than a sketch. Ultimately, McElderry decided to use Brooks's intended front as the back of the jacket, and vice versa, while Macmillan used the jacket as Brooks designed it. The file includes a copy of the finished jacket, as well as letter to English book agent Laura Cecil explaining the whole affair. Correspondence between McElderry and Hodgkin includes discussion of Susan Cooper's Newbery Award for The Grey King, as well as Nancy Winslow Parker's The Party at the Old Farm, and John Goodall's Paddy Pork's Holiday and An Edwardian Summer. Many of the letters between McElderry and Phipson include personal updates, including discussion of the upcoming Australian elections. There is also correspondence between Atheneum and Collins-Knowlton-Wing, Phipson's agent, as well as international interest in the book and a letter from Disney asking for a copy of the text.
  - A Tide Flowing, 1981
    Correspondence primarily between Phipson, McElderry and Judy Long, regarding this novel. Methuen's UK and Australian offices joined in the print run, generating correspondence between Atheneum representatives and Methuen's Bill Gobbe and Elizabeth Fulton in Australia, and Annabelle Pangborn in the UK. Phipson's used agents Curtis Brown for the project. Correspondence topics include discussion of the work's title, scientific facts about the albatross (Phipson's working title was The Wandering Albatross), differences between American and British spelling, concerns about projection and shipping, and edits to the manuscript. The dust jacket is also discussed: Methuen's edition had artwork by Ron Brooks, who did other Phipson covers, but McElderry found him unreliable and had separate cover art done by Joseph Ciardiello. Correspondence between McElderry, Long and Phipson includes personal updates, including discussion of IBBY conferences, travel, Irene Haas, Patricia Wrightson, Yoshiko Uchida's A Jar of Dreams, and the Australian filming of Phipson's novel The Cats. There is also a letter from from one Johanna Halbeisen expressing concern about the characterization of disabled people in the novel. as the main supporting character is a quadraplegic. File includes a full typscript of the novel edited in pencil, dust jacket mockups and other production material.
  - When the City Stopped, 1978
    Correspondence primarily between Phipson, McElderry, Judy Long, and Marni Hodgkin of Macmillan London, which co-published this novel with Atheneum, though under the title Keep Calm. Hodgkin left Macmillan in the middle of the publication process and correspondence resumes with Diane Denney, the new editor. Macmillan and Atheneum worked more separately than usual on this title, with Macmillan "rushing ahead" (in McElderry's words) to publish in England by spring, while the American edition was published in the fall. Most of the correspondence focuses on edits to the manuscript, though Phipson and McElderry also discuss their personal lives, including the death of McElderry's husband and the honorary doctorate she received from Mt. Holyoke. There is also correspondence with Lewis Victor Mays, who did the jacket art, and representatives at Curtis Brown, Phipson's agent. Two letters regarding other Phipson titles, Fly into Danger and The Bird Smugglers can be found at the end of the file, along with several reprints of artwork with unclear relation to When the City Stopped.
- Gail Robinson, 1982
  - Raven the Trickster
    This collection of Pacific Northwestern folk tales was originally published by Chatto & Windus in the UK and picked up by Atheneum for American publication shortly before its British printing in September 1981. The correspondence is primarily between McElderry, Dianne Denney and Anne Askwith at Chatto & Windus, and John Pickering of Georges Borchardt, Inc., which handled the American rights for the author's UK agent, Bolt & Watson. There is also correspondence with Sheila Watson of Bolt & Watson, and one letter from Robinson, who was caring for her dying mother in Canada at the time of publication. Topics includes line edits, word changes suggested by McElderry, shipping concerns, and discussion of finances for the project. Jacket art and illustrations by Joanna Troughton. One copy of the Chatto & Windus edition annotated by McElderry removed from file (item # 7381930).
- Lavinia Russ
  - April Age, 1975
    Correspondence primarily between McElderry and Russ about this sequel to Russ's novel Over the Hills and Far Away. Topics include discussion of who should make the jacket art (Russ wanted Evaline Ness, but ultimately it was designed by Harriet Barton), obtaining rights permissions from Hollis Music and The Richmond Organization as the title came from a song by William Engvick and Alec Wilder and its lyrics were printed in the front matter, proofreading by Elinor R. Weinberger, discussion of the availability of Over the Hills with Marion Bell of Scribner's Book Store, thank yous after a celebratory luncheon following the book's publication, paperback rights, shopping the book for English publication (Bodley Head, Hachette, MacDonald and Jane's, Dent, Hamish Hamilton), and the title going out of pring in 1985. McElderry and Russ also discuss a range of personal topics including many lunches out, their mutual friends, and their charity work in libraries and literacy centers. They also discuss potential future projects, including an English-language edition of Boutet de Monvill's Jeanne D'Arc; Robert Henning, Jr. of the University of Rochester's Memorial Art Gallery is included in these conversations.
  - Cyrano (unpublished), 1976
    Correspondence between Russ and McElderry regarding an unpublished novel about a girl whose family moves to New York City, forcing her to leave her beloved pet duck behind. Russ seems to have discontinued work on the novel when she became ill in May 1977.
  - Biography of the Dame of Sark, 1975